Guide to the Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer Papers MSS.642
Fales Library and Special Collections
Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer Papers
1888-2024
1945-2013
Fales Library and Special Collections
Windsor, Edie
Spyer, Thea
Kasen-Windsor, Judith
MSS.642
45 Linear Feet in 68 manuscript boxes, 2 small flat boxes, 5 oversize flat boxes, 4 flat file folders, and 31 digital carriers within 3 shared boxes.
1,552.91 Megabytes in 1,159 computer files
Edith "Edie" Windsor was a computer programmer, LGBTQ+ activist, and also known as the lead plaintiff in the landmark United States Supreme Court case United States v. Windsor, which overturned Section 3 of the Defense of Marriage Act in 2013. In 1965, Windsor began a relationship with clinical psychologist Thea Spyer. As activists, they were involved in several New York City area LGBTQ+ organizations and were longtime attendees and participants in the New York City Gay Pride Parade. The Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer Papers (1888–2024) document the personal lives, professional careers, and LGBTQ+ activism of Windsor and Spyer. The collection includes materials from their early formative years into their adulthood through photographs, correspondence, school material, and family records. Their decades-long partnership is illustrated through extensive personal photographs, correspondence, and household files, with a particular emphasis on their identity as a lesbian couple, and their struggles with Spyer's multiple sclerosis. Their desire to marry is documented in planning files, photographs, and digital video recording of the 2007 ceremony. Windsor's professional career as a computer programmer, and Spyer's work as a clinical psychologist are documented through resumes, correspondence, newsletters, and published articles. Event files and organizational records dating from the 1980s to the 2020s document a variety of LGBTQ+ organizations in which Windsor and Spyer were involved throughout their lifetimes. Windsor's pivotal role in United States v. Windsor is documented through her legal files, correspondence, press coverage, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Judith Kasen-Windsor, Edie Windsor's widow, in June 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.032. Kasen-Windsor donated an accretion of paper and electronic records in December 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.055.
Appraisal
The following items were removed from the collection during processing: 39 born-digital carriers (blank; commercial; and duplicate material); 1 audiocassette; 2 commercial DVDs (exterior covers of documentary films were retained as objects); 12 cartons of duplicate print material and out of scope correspondence; and 5 cartons of empty slide carousels and their storage boxes. Three cartons of images were separated from the collection using the following directives: blurry/out of focus; children pictured alone (e.g., children of friends); portraits or candids of individual friends without context; home improvement (e.g., close-up images of pipes, drywall, and tools); repetitive yard images without context; and close-up images of decor without context.
Arrangement
Organized into three series, with each further divided into subseries:
Series I. Personal
Subseries I.A. Edie Windsor
Subseries I.B. Thea Spyer
Subseries I.C. Household
Series II. Professional
Subseries II.A. Edie Windsor
Subseries II.B. Thea Spyer
Series III. Activism
Subseries III.A. Events and Appearances
Subseries III.B. Organizations
Subseries III.C. United States v. Windsor
Material within each series is arranged alphabetically and grouped by subject, with the exception of Subseries III.A. and III.C. which are arranged in chronological order.
Biographical Note on Edith "Edie" Windsor
Edith "Edie" Windsor (Schlain) (1929–2017) was a computer engineer and LGBTQ+ activist best known for her role as the lead plaintiff in the landmark 2013 Supreme Court case United States v. Windsor, which struck down Section 3 of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA).
Windsor worked for IBM from the late 1950s through the 1980s, and later founded her own software consulting firm, PC Classics, Inc., which assisted many LGBTQ+ organizations in modernizing their mailing and membership systems.
In 1965, Windsor began a lifelong relationship with Thea Spyer. The couple became engaged in 1967, with the hope that same-sex marriage would eventally become legal in the United States. In the 1970s, Spyer was diagnosed with multiple sclerosis and as her condition worsened, Windsor chose to take early retirement from IBM in 1975 in order to become her full-time caregiver. The couple entered into a domestic partnership in 1993 and eventually married in Canada in 2007 when it became legal to do so there.
After Spyer's death in 2009, Windsor sought the federal estate tax exemption available to surviving spouses but was denied under DOMA. This led her to challenge the law, resulting in the United States Supreme Court 2013 decision in United States v. Windsor, a historic victory for marriage equality.
As an activist, Windsor worked closely with a number of LGBTQ+ organizations including the East End Gay Organization (EEGO), Services and Advocacy for LGBT Elders (SAGE), and Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC). She was also a longtime attendee and participant in the New York City Gay Pride Parade.
Following the Supreme Court decision, Windsor's profile as a public figure grew significantly. She became a celebrated LGBTQ+ advocate, receiving widespread recognition and numerous awards for her contributions to civil rights and social justice. Windsor married Judith Kasen in 2016. After her death in 2017, Windsor's legacy is carried on through her wife Judith Kasen-Windsor, as well as through various organizations including the Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer Foundation; The Stonybrook Southampton Edie Windsor Healthcare Center; and the Edie Windsor Visitor Center at Hetrick-Martin Institute.
Biographical Note on Thea Spyer
Thea Spyer (1931–2009) was a clinical psychologist and LGBTQ+ activist. Born in Amsterdam, she and her family emigrated to the United States in the 1940s. After earning a Ph.D. in Clinical Psychology from Adelphi University, Spyer moved to New York City and served as Director of the Psychiatric Clinic at the International Center for the Disabled and then as a Clinical Consultant in Rehabilitation at St. Vincent's Hospital in Westchester. She eventually started her own private practice, continuing to see patients until her death in 2009.
In 1965, Spyer began a relationship with Edie Windsor which lasted over 40 years. The couple became engaged in 1967, entered a domestic partnership in 1993, and married in Toronto, Canada, in 2007. Spyer was diagnosed with multiple sclerosis in the mid-1970s and eventually needed full-time care and used a wheelchair.
After Spyer's death, her wife Edie was denied the federal estate tax exemption for surviving spouses under the Defense of Marriage Act. Windsor's legal challenge led to the 2013 decision on the United States Supreme Court case United States v. Windsor.
Spyer's work in the mental health field, especially related to the LGBTQ+ community, is commemorated through the Thea Spyer Center at the Callen-Lorde Community Health Center and the Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer Foundation.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
This collection chronicles the more than forty-year relationship and marriage of Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer, providing a unique perspective on LGBTQ+ life and community from the late 20th century into the early 21st century. It also highlights their shared activism and Windsor's later emergence as a cultural icon through her landmark United States Supreme Court Case, United States v. Windsor, which struck down key parts of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA).
Material related to Edie and Thea's early lives as children and young adults offers a clearer understanding of them as individuals before they became a couple in 1965. The impact of World War II and post-War culture on both of their early lives is represented in this collection through Windsor's photographs, school ephemera, and correspondence, documenting her life growing up in Philadelphia, going to college, and working summers in Atlantic City. Contrasting this with Thea's experience being born in the Netherlands in the 1930s and, because her family was Jewish, fleeing the country and eventually moving to the United States in the early 1940s. This collection contains Thea's photographs, correspondence, citizenship documentation, and family ephmera.
Edie and Thea's life together is documented through images and materials that illustrate their vibrant social life centered within the LGBTQ+ community, featuring decades of gatherings, vacations, beach days, celebrations, and their 2007 wedding. Thea's diagnosis of multiple sclerosis in the mid-1970s also impacted their lives, especially as her MS progressed through the years, with her eventually requiring full time caregiving and use of a wheelchair. Their gradual adjustments through the years to providing Thea with more accessibility in their living spaces and beyond are evident in images, correspondence, travel documents, and in apartment and house renovation plans. Planning files, photographs, and a digital video recording of their 2007 wedding in Toronto, Canada, document a same-sex couple whose commitment to marriage required traveling abroad, due to legal restrictions in the U.S. These materials also reflect the challenges they faced as elderly individuals with chronic illnesses, underscoring the deep personal significance of their decision to marry.
Work files in this collection for both Edie and Thea provide insight into the lives of women working during the 1950s through 1980s, specifically in predominantly male-dominated fields. Windsor worked as a computer programmer for IBM and as a consultant, where not only was she one of the only women, but she was also not out as a lesbian to her co-workers. Her programming source code, consulting business client files, and involvement in various professional groups also provides documentation on the developing role of computers and programming for work and home during this time.
This collection also follows Edie and Thea's activism in a variety of LGBTQ+ community organizations, many of which had specific focuses that appealed to them, including geographic location such as NFWFW (North Fork Women for Women) or EEGO (East End Gay Organization), or SAGE (Services and Advocacy for LGBT Elders) and OLOC (Old Lesbians Organizing for Change), both organizations concenered with the care and rights of elderly gay people. Event and appearance files within this collection document how Edie and Thea's social lives and activism were intertwined, and in later years reflect the increased social demands on Windsor after her United States Supreme Court decision in 2013, which made her a highly sought after personality for appearances. Additionally, this collection contains documentation on Windsor's United State Supreme Court Case, United States v. Windsor which struck down key parts of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA). This material accumulated by Windsor includes correspondence, press conference talking points, photographs, press clippings, and legal documentation.
Same-sex marriage -- Law and legislation; LGBTQ+ weddings; LGBTQ+ couples; Women political activists.; Gay pride celebrations -- New York (State) -- New York; Gay pride parades; Lesbian activists; Computer programming; Gay liberation movement -- New York (State) -- New York; Civil rights.; Lesbian culture; Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); LGBTQ+ clubs and organizations; Appointment books.; Correspondence.; Multiple sclerosis; Wheelchairs; Lesbian community; Lesbian couples -- United States; Older lesbians; Same-sex marriage -- United States; Gay couples -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Marriage law -- United States; Lesbian disabled people; Caregivers; Persons with Disabilities; Kasen-Windsor, Judith; United States. Supreme Court; Senior Action in a Gay Environment (Organization); Services and Advocacy for Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual & Transgender Elders; East End Gay Organization; Kaplan, Roberta A.; International Business Machines Corporation; Institute for the Crippled and Disabled; Old Lesbians Organizing for Change; United States. Defense of Marriage Act
- Series I. Personal, 1888-2023; 1950-2000; 25 Linear Feet in 39 manuscript boxes, 2 small flat boxes, 4 oversize flat boxes, and 1 flat-file folder; 472.91 Megabytes in 441 computer files
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Edie Windsor
  Subseries I.B. Thea Spyer
  Subseries I.C. Household
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material focused on the personal lives of Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer as individuals, specifically during their childhood, teen, and young adult years before they met in 1965. This series also contains material related to their daily lives and events shared as a committed couple for over 40 years.
  - Subseries I.A. Edie Windsor, circa 1900s-2023; 17.80 Linear Feet in 24 manuscript boxes and 5 oversized flat boxes.
    This subseries documents Edie Windsor's life as an individual, with particular emphasis on her teen and single adult years, as well as her life after the death of Thea and later marriage to Judith Kasen-Windsor.
    Early images in slide and print form and disassembled albums in this subseries date from the 1930s to early 1950s, tracing her life from a teen to young adult years. These images frequently feature friends and family, providing glimpses into life during World War II, post-War life, and Windsor's fondness for the beach and socializing. This is especially true of the images of her summers spent working in Atlantic City during the late 1940s and early 1950s. Her brief marriage to Saul Wiener (Windsor) and subsequent divorce are also documented in this subseries. Images in this subseries also illustrate her post-divorce life in New York City in the 1950s, highlighting her growing connection to the lesbian community through photographs of parties and trips with friends and romantic partners to local beach destinations. Posed portrait photographs of Windsor span from the 1960s to 2017. Images of Edie and Thea together are in Series I.C.
    School materials includes Windsor's high school yearbook, report cards, class notes, and papers. College-era material consists of photographs, class schedules, and school newsletters from Rittenhouse College, as well as documents from Windsor's graduate studies at New York University and Harvard University/Radcliffe College during the 1960s.
    Material related to Windsor's family includes photographs, estate documents, and correspondence for James "Jack" Schlain, Celia "Cele" Schlain, sister Delphina "Dolly", brother Edmund "Blackie", and cousins. The subseries also contains early photographs of relatives dating from the 1900s through the 1960s.
    Windsor's calendars and appointment books (1960s–2017), notebooks, budget and expense reports, and personal correspondence offer insights into her daily life. Her correspondence in this subseries notably increased in volume following key events in her life that resonated with the LGBTQ+ community, including the death of Thea Spyer in 2009 and the landmark 2013 United States Supreme Court case United States v. Windsor.
    Windsor's interest in health and wellness is reflected in notebooks tracking her progress with a substantial selection of anti-smoking, diet, and exercise-related print materials. Items from her later years, especially after 2013, include correspondence and photographs with her second wife, Judith Kasen-Windsor, whom she married in 2016. The subseries also includes condolence cards sent to Kasen-Windsor after Windsor's death in 2017, as well as Windsor's obituary, press clippings, and memorial service program.
    - Address Books, 1985-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8-9, Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8-9, Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 1990-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7-12, Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 1999-2007 (Box 4, Folder 2-8)
    - Appointment and Date Books, 2007-2017 (Box 5, Folder 1-8, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Artwork -- Edie "Don't Postpone Joy" Print Portrait by Abigail Gray Swartz, 2020 (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Artwork -- Signed Art Poster for Photographer Marian Roth "Underwater" Exhibition, undated (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Articles and Press Clippings, 2011-2017 (Box 6, Folder 4-8, Box 69, Folder 1-10)
    - Awards, Citations, Proclamations, 2011-2018 (Box 6, Folder 9, Box 72, Folder 3-4, Box 74, Folder 1-3, Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Statements and Summaries, circa 2009-2016 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Birth Certificate and Related, 1929, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Books and Memoirs -- Literary Agent Agreement and Related, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Books and Memoirs -- A Wild and Precious Life Correspondence, Edits, Event-Related Material, 2017-2020 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
    - Candid Images of Edie, 1963-2010
      - Photographs, 1963-1964 (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Slide Images, January 1975 (Box 58, Folder 2)
      - Photographs, circa 1990s (Box 58, Folder 3)
      - Photographs, March 30, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Photograph, 2010 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Charitable Contributions Documentation, 2011-2016 (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
    - Childhood -- Photographs, circa 1935-early 1940s (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - "The Club" Joint Real Estate Venture Documentation, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Austern, Norman, 1960-1967 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Cohen, Barbara, 2015 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Bless Bless Productions, 2007-2015 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Ellison Family, 1959-1972 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Faderman, Lillian, 2014 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Kaplan, Roberta "Robbie" and Family, 2012-2016 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Lecesne, James, 2015-2017 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Lewis, Zoe, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Mayer, Yisroel, 2011-2012 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Meyer, Susan, 2013-2015 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Morrison, Jim, 2011 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Nusio, Kimberly, 2011-2014 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Proud, B., 2016-2017 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Renna, Cathy, 2013-2016 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Rovinsky, Selma, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Seligma, June, 1956-1961, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Spyer Family Members, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical -- Varga, Margit, 1965-1976 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1950-2008 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 6-8, Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 2010-2012 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 2013 (Box 10, Folder 4-5, Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 2014-2015 (Box 11, Folder 2-5)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 2016-2017 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, undated (Box 12, Folder 4-8)
    - Correspondence Between Edie and Wife Judith Kasen-Windsor, 2016-2017 (Box 8, Folder 3, Box 13, Folder 1, Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to Edie and Wife Judith Kasen-Windsor, 2016-2017 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence of Judith Kasen-Windsor, 2016-2023, undated (Box 13, Folder 4-6, Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Desk Calendar, 1961 (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Desk Calendar, 2011 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Dream Journals, 1964-1975 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
    - Edie Windsor Way Philadelphia Street Sign, and Photograph of Installed Sign, undated (Box 76, Folder 3, Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Edie with Friends Images, 1950-2017
      - Photographs, 1950-1951 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - Photographs, 1955 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - Photograph, Spring 1957 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      - Photographs, 1987, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      - Photographs, circa 2010-2017 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Education -- Delta Gamma Pi Fraternity Press Clipping, circa 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Education -- West Philadelphia High School Yearbook and Ephemera, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Education -- Class Notes and Papers, 1946-1950 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Education -- Rittenhouse College, 1947-1948
      - Newsletters and Ephemera (Box 15, Folder 5, Box 72, Folder 1)
      - Photographs of Edie and Tennis Team, Friend Rene (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - Education -- Hunter College Academic Records, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Education -- New York University Admissions Material and Academic Records, 1953-1958, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Education -- New York University Diploma for Master of Science, 1957 (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Education -- Radcliffe College/Harvard University Ephemera, 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
    - Education -- Radcliffe College/Harvard University Computer Programming Class Notes, 1960-1961 (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - Education -- Speech and Accent Correction Lessons, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Education -- French Language Class Notes and Exercises, 1977-1979 (Box 15, Folder 11-13, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Education -- Hebrew Language Class Notes and Exercises, circa 1980s (Box 16, Folder 3-6)
    - Education -- C Computer Language Programming Class Notes, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Education -- Math Class Notes, 1994-1995 (Box 16, Folder 8-9, Box 17, Folder 1-3)
    - Education -- Writing Class Notes and Short Stories, 2000-2001 (Box 17, Folder 4-8)
    - Education -- High School Reunion Information, 2006 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Egypt and Greece Trip, November 11-December 1, 1984
      - Planning Material and Image Title Lists from Slide Storage Boxes (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Slides and Photographs (Box 59, Folder 8-10)
    - Egypt and Greece Trip -- Slide Images, February 1987 (Box 59, Folder 11)
    - Expenses and Income Ledger Pages, 1952, 1954 (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Expenses Notebook, 1952-1965 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Family -- Celia "Cele" Schlain (Mother), 1913, 1920s-1950s
      - Cards and Letters, 1913, 1920s-1950s (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence with Edie, 1957-1979 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Family -- Celia "Cele" Schlain (Mother) 80th Birthday Party, March 11, 1972
      - Identifying Notes for Images (Box 57, Folder 10)
      - Photographs and Contact Sheets (Box 59, Folder 12)
    - Family -- Delphina "Dolly" Rieder (Sister), 1942-1970
      - Correspondence, 1943-1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Photograph of Dolly and Husband Frederick Rieder, 1942 (Box 59, Folder 13)
    - Family -- Edie and Family Group Photographs, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 59, Folder 19)